all right everybody you are back
this is the jack murphy live podcast i
am jack murphy you can find me on
twitter at jack murphy live
the website is jack murphy live.com the
book
democrat to deplorable you can find that
on amazon right now tells the story of
2016 and
what's going to happen in 2020
and if you're interested in the liminal
order come down and check us out we have
three core values
masculinity brotherhood and sovereignty
and we work every day to enhance those
in our lives and in our culture
that's liminal hyphen order dot com come
down check that out today i have a
repeat
guest one of my favorite people to talk
to in the whole world
mr john robb john robb is an author of a
book called brave new war
fantastically prescient written many
years ago something everyone should read
to understand the world today
he was a special forces veteran or is a
veteran
he's a technologist a writer a thinker
john it's an honor to have you how you
doing this morning
oh thank you for having me on jack um
yeah i'm doing great
fantastic for long time listeners of the
jack murphy live podcast you know that
john is a regular
guest he was on number 11 and number 22
and i highly suggest listening
to both of those to get some more
background and context for what we're
going to talk about today
but we're just going to jump right into
it because
we've got a lot to talk about and
there's a lot going on and so
john let's just go for it where are we
today john what is happening what are
you seeing
what's on your mind today we got a
number of topics to get to but what's
going on with you
what are we seeing right now john uh
maybe if we just focus on the
what's right in front of us the election
yeah and then we can dive into deeper
topics you know from that um
so the election um you know what looked
like
would be a trump you know uh victory
back in january uh economy was rolling
uh his support was intact uh was all
thrown into shambles by covet
and covid changed everything changed the
the whole dynamic
in the country um and you know
the standard political things it's you
know damage the economy put people out
of work
uh you know damage to society
everyone's uh upset by it but uh
what was interesting to me is that that
it actually
damaged the mechanism by which the
trumps insurgency operated
um kind of like disruptive
change topics every day uh type approach
that was so effective in the uh
previous campaign right and throughout
the last three four years
um in that regard it's it's useful to
maybe think of uh
you know think of covid as kind of a
russian winter
and its impact on a maneuver force and
uh you know the
trump's insurgency is a maneuver for it
it maneuvers from topic to topic fast
transients
uh it makes it impossible for the
opposition
to uh think cogently uh because
they're by the time they mount an
argument against what you're
talking about you're on to the next
topic and uh
the conditions are changing so quickly
is that they become you know disoriented
and overloaded
um covet you know changed that dynamic
it made it
uh it bogged down that that that
strategy
just like a german tanks in russian
winter
or or the the fast maneuver forces of
napoleon
was known for maneuverability and and
speed
um and once that maneuverability was
lost you know it's just
it's just a grind um and uh
that made it possible for you know biden
and and harris to kind of sit back and
it's almost a non-campaign
they're really pretty much absent from
the from the field and they're just not
engaging and they're just letting
you know kovid take its toll and you
know this
you know just letting the letting the uh
what i would say kind of the guerrilla
forces
the resistance has always been and the
tribes of the left
have always fought in the moral realm uh
which is really guerrilla warfare
it's uh uh always taking a a moral
approach to warfare
trying to break apart the uh trump
support
and cleave off pieces of it into
non-cooperative
centers of gravity um and uh
it's kind of like the role of the
cossacks and harassing
napoleon's forces is retreating from
moscow
it's very effective and it does most of
the heavy lifting in the campaign and in
this case we have
not only the you know tribal groups
online
we also have a tribal media that's
pretty much totally capitulated to the
to the tribes
and just recently we saw with the the
effort on censorship it
it's uh uh also the platforms are making
extra efforts
to kind of toe the line and gain favor
with the uh
with the tribes so um yeah they're doing
the heavy lifting in the work
so yeah go ahead please you said that
covid changed things and
uh first i know i told people to listen
to the old stuff but i do want to give a
little bit of context
uh you know when you say maneuver
warfare you know that's trump acting
very quickly moving quickly behind enemy
lines
disruptive you said fast transients you
know that's how he uses twitter just
shooting things out there
for people to chase after like 80d you
know dogs chasing squirrels
and disrupting people's flow and you're
saying that covid
was something that just bogged him down
it's something he had to talk about the
same thing every day
it made everybody very fearful and
scared and one thing that you did note
in one of your early global guerrilla or
earlier reports and you should follow
everybody follow john rob on patreon
the single best patreon in the universe
no question about it
uh you said that uh that
kovid took us from uh circumstances of
networked politics networked insurgency
to
networked tribal tribalized networks
what does that mean
so that we can use that frame of
reference for the rest of this
conversation
yeah um it's it's the arc of what
uh how networked organizations have
developed over time
and i first saw networked organizations
in in the iraqi insurgency
and it kind of opened what i called an
open source insurgency
we had 70 different small groups all
working in concert
even without you know standard pathways
of communication
like but they were able to take on a
larger enemy
and that proved very innovative very
effective
uh then it moved into network protest uh
open source protests that we saw in
egypt we saw an occupy we saw
in puerto rico when they took out the
governor uh
that protest movement was you know
effective at mobilizing and focusing in
on one
goal and and driving it home um
that morphed into politics network
politics we saw in 2016 is that uh that
kind of mobilization capability that uh
innovativeness was able to translate
into getting
a candidate into the white house and in
the case of trump
um then we had a kind of a process that
that developed over the last three years
where uh
you had kind of a three four years it
had
trump's open source insurgency you know
kind of a political
insurgency uh constantly disrupting and
then you you know
trying to break apart anything that they
saw would that would
you know lock things down and then you
had the resistance that was fighting
that was trying to drive consensus on
different issues
now that's i thought over time that that
would stabilize that we would be able to
turn
you know network decision making social
decision making to something that's uh
useful long term um that
it could be part of our decision making
process along you know with markets and
bureaucracies and uh
you know the kind of you know national
kind of sentiment that we've had in the
past
and um what happened is that kovit
entered the scene and and it turned
these
uh open source organizations into
something that looked more like tribes
because of the threat kind of the
existential threat that
that coveted represented and we saw it
you know developed most quickly on the
left
uh and um what we saw was a you know
tribal groups form around different
topics that they
opposed um and these tribes are are
relatively cohesive but and they're uh
very aggressive and
uh with tribalism you see uh in group
out group dynamic you see
a fictive kinship develop between the
people inside the tribe and the people
outside the tribe
get zero empathy uh they're you know
enemies they're evil they're
absolute evil and uh when i
you know accorded any kind of you know
you know standard uh
decency that you would inside you know a
functioning
country so uh yeah so we were in this
kind of tribalism and and tribalism i
think is you know ultimately just
destabilizing it's not something that we
could we could we could like
survive if it keep continues to progress
let me ask you a question about this
i kind of always thought that if aliens
came from outer space that we would
unify
around a common enemy and that a lot of
our tribal distinctions would go away
there was a moment in march where i
kind of felt like that was happening
with corona i can't remember
exactly what it was but there was a
sense i remember tweeting about it like
man maybe this is the existential threat
that unifies us beyond our tribal
politics and whatnot
but that quickly dissipated two two
questions
one like how and why and and then two
does that mean that if the aliens come
we're still gonna be divided
okay um first you know why did it happen
i mean that was
what we've experienced in march was a
consensus a network consensus
and um we all wanted to do something
to end covet early on i mean it started
developing in late february and by
you know mid-march we were all on board
uh what even before the government
actually
acted um people stopped or started to
stop flying
they were already you know thousands of
companies doing work from home
before the government even had its first
uh
you know lockdown order
um but the thing is uh
you know that kind of consensus needs
kind of a leadership
function it needs to be kind of led and
and you know
they need to participate in it if there
was somebody actually out there
doing even a youtube thing you know for
a couple hours every day
uh trying to figure out how to solve
different problems like masks
the problem with masks is that we could
have had a you know cottage industry
developed almost overnight back in march
to develop masks uh instead you know
everything was kicked up to the
government level and then this
combination of agencies and
governors and the president and
everything else and uh
they were confused as to what to do um
and uh they kind of dictated all sorts
of strange stuff like
don't wear masks because they would be
taking away from
from uh hospital workers and frontline
workers
uh kind of getting that meme out there
and that kind of screwed people's out
people up in regards to you know the
effectiveness of masks
um and then they were unsure as to you
know
how to you know institute a lockdown
uh you know you know the the messaging
was all messed up and
there's a there's a couple things that
in terms of our response i think that we
we screwed up and i don't i don't know
if uh
i'm pretty sure that it no matter who
was in the white house we would have
screwed those things up
anyway yeah but um by abdicating this
kind of consensus to the
and letting the government take control
um with its
kind of top-down information model uh
ended up
breaking things it broke the consensus
over time as they screwed up
as things rolled forward a descent
formed
and the descent was like wait a second
this is not making sense
this is not uh coherent um and they
started attacking it
and uh you know the consensus rallied
around certain things that they thought
would be the most important maybe the
tone out of the white house or something
and then um uh you know we saw that
consensus break up and
now we're here where we are in kind of a
management phase
we might have always been on this
direction towards a kind of a managed
virus phase but
this is where we're at now would we uh
divide over alien threat depends on how
aggressive it is if they're
you know i'm sure there would be a huge
group of people that would want to give
in right away
you know it's in a possible battle we
shouldn't fight it
we would would gain by the uh by
working under them or you know being
subservient and
we're seeing that that that probably
would be the case right
right my hopes and dreams for the
outside existential threat unifying
our warring tribes is probably a fantasy
huh
well i mean you got to lead it too i
mean you know if you're not leading
the uh consensus you're not leading this
open source movement
you're not uh and you're not getting
them to participate
and you you're not going to see this
thing last
um and it would have been effective for
months but the thing is uh
you know we didn't we didn't see any
leadership of that type of merge and
and you know makes sense because uh i
mean everybody in the
the political leadership class is is
doesn't think like that they think in
terms of bureaucracies they think in
terms of
you know standard traditional tv media
they don't think in terms of anything
else outside of that
yeah yeah do you not to get too far down
this avenue but do you think that the
trump
administration or trump or anyone up
there has
given you any signs that they understand
the
world in a similar way that you do in
terms of
you know needing to needing to lead this
emerging you know consensus
or just the the network effect are the
fast transients that he shoots out
are they deliberate in this context or
are they just
his personality spazzing out over
twitter you know i always wonder if he
was just suited for the moment or if he
fit himself to the moment or
or whatever do you see any evidence that
the trump administration
understands the network framework like
you do
um well i think the president has
certain
dynamics in the way he approaches the
media and approaches
communications and learns that works
well within the
network framework he doesn't get the
full feedback loop
uh that you would if you were he's a he
tends to try to do that in person
like a classic sales guy yeah you know
he likes to see the response in those
big rallies
um which again you know that's one of
the things that covets screwed up right
dampened everything
plus getting everybody sick right so
it's like toned everything down right at
the
right at the most crucial moment um
i i do know that there are people inside
and and
and around uh around him that did get it
um but you know it's hard i guess
you know it's very chaotic and the
chairs get shuffled quite a bit
so um i don't know if there's any
comprehensive or cohesive
strategy in that regard right right well
that's a shame i do know as well that
there are some people in there that sort
of do get it
but to the extent that there's a
comprehensive strategy that reflects
that
i'm not so sure about and you know it's
not necessarily a massive condemnation i
mean this is stuff that's evolving
minute by minute second by second uh you
know you're one of the few people out
there who see this framework and can
can point to evidence to support your
theories it's one thing i always really
like about you john you're not just a
theorist you're not just
writing fantasy blog posts and wondering
about the future you're actually
creating models and testing them
looking for evidence to match your your
theories and then evolving them from
there
and so you know oh yeah you're welcome
thank you
um you know you've taught me quite a bit
over the last few years here and so it's
not necessarily the end of the world if
the administration
you know a 70 some year old guy
and a bunch of old cronies up there can
understand the world in such an advanced
way but that's part of the reason why we
do what we do
we do know that people administration
follow our socials and read the stuff
that we put out and so
you know we i think that we do have some
sort of influence so
three of the topics that we want to talk
about today were
coo mechanics civil war triggers
and tribal totalitarianism
that last one is a tongue twister yeah i
know i even had trouble typing it out so
um now that we've sort of established so
this evolution of how the network
insurgencies and politics
have evolved to this point now where
we're splitting off into sort of a
tribal
element based around empathetic triggers
and if we want to talk about that a
little bit
i would be interested because i think
this is a very key component to
how we're organizing empathetic triggers
what are they john and how how do they
work on us
and what is it going to lead to right um
well uh the idea is that you know we are
being rewired our minds are being
rewired by our interaction with social
media
um it's you know marcia mcclellan you
know the famous
kind of media prophet had a model based
on this
uh and uh
what happens is that you know and i've
been doing this since the dawn of social
media
helped build it back in 2001 and i you
know so i got into theorizing how it was
actually
impacting the way we thought or think um
is that in the past you know in the
printed world we used to
read things in long form and that
you know we take it back in isolation
read it and they
form an opinion and come forward and
discuss that
uh in the social media driven world the
technology is has enabled a volume of
information that's way more than we can
process at any given moment
and that volume is is has forced us to
change
the way we approach it the way we
consume it and
one of the ways that has proven to be
the most effective is
something i call pattern matching is
that you look for little bits and pieces
of information the posts that matter to
you
um and um
posts that fit a pattern that you're
curating that you're you're interested
in um
and you know you you just kind of take
them out of this
out of the stream and you you click them
into the pattern like a you know
puzzle piece and you go okay uh
that's an example of this or this is you
know another example of this pattern
over here
um those patterns over time have
developed into the kind of the basis of
the kind of tribalism we're seeing and
you know traditionally a tribe is like
a group of people that come together
usually related by blood but you know
uh tribe expanded beyond you know direct
blood relations uh
is that you have a reason for
why you are better together and that
kind of core reason and those rituals
associated with that
are kind of the basis for the tribe um
and that you know it's kind of a
positive notion of you know
that we're we're better because we're
you know helping each other and um
that doesn't work in the online world it
doesn't work in the modern world
uh there you know people can't agree on
what they're for
okay put two people in a room and they
just there's always disagreement on what
you're
for um or how you interpret it because
many of the values most of the values
that we develop now
even if those values with religious
bases are subjectively derived or
tweaked or whatever and that subjective
element
makes them very difficult to
uh
equalize across people uh you know come
to agreement on
and so what we can agree on and
apparently this is this is
you know effective is that we can agree
on what we hate
what we dislike um and in the case of
the online world
a pattern of what they consider racist
behavior
has you know racist behavior resists and
this and this and this and this
and here's the pattern and here's where
it shows up
uh and you know as social media provided
posts people
took those examples and snapped them
into the pattern that
pattern of racism has proven it
something that people could rally behind
become a tribe behind
and so the empathy piece comes in and
this is this is critical here and this
is really what makes a tribe really
solid
is that you know empathy
can be triggered very easily online okay
it you know you're you're in this
pattern matching mode and then all of a
sudden you see a video
like the george floyd video and it hits
you like a raw
you know uh thunderbolt it just it hits
you right in the right between the eyes
and uh the empathy triggers and you
become
george you have you know that knee on
your neck and you get really mad
and you know since this trigger is part
of a you know demonstration that this
pattern of systemic racism this pattern
of colonialism this pattern of
of fascism exists you know you
become part of that tribe you become you
form a kinship bond
because empathy isn't what you most
people think it is it i think it's a
strong
form of pre-verbal communication is that
it allows you to when somebody's telling
you a story is that you become
them okay and they it and it's actually
shown that
that you modeled their minds that at the
time
if there's a hero fighting a a a beast
you become the hero you you see the
beast in your eyes your teeth grit your
hands tight on the on the weapon um and
if you're the
if you're the victim you feel that knee
on your neck you feel the
the depression of the sit the moment
and it changes you physically but
there's a mental transfer
and that mental model is built
immediately in your head it's a huge
transfer of information
and it's transformative and it's the
basis of that empathy can
embed empathetic connection is the basis
of tribalism i feel
i afford unlimited empathy to the people
inside my tribe
and i afford none to the
precious to the evil opponents
um and that allows you know that tribal
dynamic is
the basis of warfare you know we see it
in war right you know
ginning up you know kind of sentiment
for world war ii or any major war
is that the enemy has to be completely
devoid of any you know positive
characteristics they have to be
the absolute enemy yeah and that we're
in this for the just and the good and
they're
you know an enemy of mankind yeah
that's uh you're triggering something in
me right now because i don't feel very
good listening to that
so many things come to mind so uh if you
can form a try based on pattern
recognition around empathetic triggers
and you create a system like the
intersectional intersectionalists have
the critical racer you have
whereby like every event out there is a
traumatizing event
then if you frame it that way you can
really trigger a number of empathetic
reactions from people
if everything is now oppression
everything is now a knee on the neck
there's institutional racism everywhere
there's sexism everywhere there's
xenophobia everywhere
and it's like you're creating a system
where like
your view your perceptive tools just see
those those triggers
in everything everywhere whether or not
they're really true
and that's a very powerful force of
getting people getting people together
um i wonder
you know are people very clearly tuned
into this phenomenon and so specifically
like
sending out empathetic triggers into the
world
or is it that they just it's just trial
and error trial and error and something
goes out there and
it sticks and it's really the system
that we've created that is eliciting
these
this this transmission of these
empathetic you know sort of
triggers and pattern triggers right so
it's the system that's actually
drawing us into this right it's a little
bit of both
i mean there are definitely people who
are constantly i mean they're curators
right um and they're influencers and
they're people who
actively seek out empathetic triggers
they actively seek out
examples of patterns that they curate
um anti-fascist patterns uh anti-racism
patterns anti-sexism patterns
anti-colonial patterns um constantly
taking whatever they find and posting it
and sharing it
um and trying to build a following
around that and the more effective the
empathetic trigger the bigger the
reaction they get from that
just one more comment on this what's
fascinating to me is like as a
as someone who's done a lot of
visualization i used to
be an amateur muay thai fighter and we
really sat down and visualized what the
fight was going to look like and put
ourselves in that situation
i remember interviewing john fitch of a
ufc fighter
a tremendous ufc fighter one of the best
of all time and he would tell me about
his visualization exercises where he
would be driving and listening
and doing it in his head and like his
body let's start getting tense and he
starts getting
his heart rate gets up because just like
you said you know if you can put your
mind
into that environment you actually begin
to feel these things and become
become as powerful as reality because
and then and then in a visualization
sense you do it over and over again so
you become accustomed to stressful
situation
and that when you get to something that
may be actually novel for you in the
physical world
in your mental world it's something that
you've already tackled a number of times
so this is not like some abstract crazy
esoteric
theory about uh having uh you know
chemical reactions in your brain
actually
change your perception of the world and
your ability to interact with it and how
your emotions
evolve or or what you react how you
react from a certain
stressor or certain circumstances so
when you tell me
that by simply sending around images or
videos or memes
right memes are all in the same vibe
that create an empathetic reaction
that it actually has a physical
physiological chemical change in you
it changes you it changes your
perception of the world and then in my
conversations with jordan hall he really
helped me understand how like
there's so much data in the world that
our job isn't to actually seek out and
absorb data it's actually to filter data
and so
we're training our filters to narrow it
into things that make sense for us and
work for us and so
these empathetic triggers and the
pattern recognition it actually is like
training people's perception filters to
zero in on these particular things
right then they then you just start
seeing them everywhere
so it's all it's part technology part
social media
part the distribution networks that we
have that are destroying like our social
cohesion because now
we have a million different empathetic
tribes or fictive kinships
shared imagined orders i was talking
about this last night on tim poole's
podcast
and uh now that there's instead of just
walter cronkite saying to you hey here's
how we're going to think and feel about
things and everybody gets
one set of images of the you know the
troops in vietnam or whatever it was
you know you can predict sort of how
people are going to react but now it's
just a million people talking to a
million
people right but what we've seen though
is like a
market consolidation in the empathetic
triggering
market right like there may be a million
people out there with millions stories
but where they're actually coalescing
right now and q anon's one too yeah i
mean these patterns
these patterns um they solve a problem i
was working on a long time ago
and how do you keep an open source
movement going over time right
yeah and usually when they achieve the
goal
like either kick mubarak out or the
governor goes or
or uh you know the government topples
right is that okay they've achieved it
it's over
what the first solution was to turn the
candidate
into a weapon which was i think the the
trump's insurgency didn't
put the candidate trump into office they
put the weapon trump into office that's
right i mean what he did is
he was disruptive and that's what they
wanted they want somebody to disrupt
a system they saw as negative to their
futures
and he as long as he continued that he
got the support and his
support stayed steady at 42 throughout
his entire presidency
yeah um they kept the open source
insurgency
alive this brings it to another level
it's a
it's an open source mechanism which is
the pattern right
uh you know the pattern of anti-racism
of the anti-racist tribe
and that thing has durability right uh
it is curated by millions of people um
and
it's uh it's got this kind of central
premise that that
uh can continue to expand and absorb
every
bit of information that could possibly
be attached to it it can be brought down
to the individual level and this is
really where it gets dangerous is that
uh it you know being curated and
and maintained by so many people they
can you know apply it to everybody
every individual every action that you
make it then can be
adjudicated based on this pattern um
you know and that's the basis of you
know people taking videos
of of some random individual doing xyz
and then
uploading it and then having the the
crowd enforce it
and force some kind of damage on them i
mean attack them get them
you know strip them of the job and strip
them of their
of their you know ability to be on the
platform
et cetera et cetera et cetera and that's
kind of the
the key towards the kind of the tribal
totalitarianism i was talking about
that's one of the topics yeah we're
definitely going to get to that
definitely going to get to that uh
you mentioned earlier you know what
happened with the hunter biden story on
facebook uh
with them banning any links to the new
york post story first of all new york
post one of the oldest newspapers in
america founded by alexander hamilton
you know maybe they do some sensational
stuff but they've been doing journalism
for two centuries
and to say that it's some sort of
fraudulent organization
is just a crock of crap and uh
what struck me about that is that the
folks
in charge seem to feel like they need to
change the rules of the game
uh rather than change ideas and and i
think it's just another
sort of uh testimony to the fact that
like
we're not being we're not changing
people's minds about things we're not
changing the ideas we're not convincing
people to see things another way
what we're doing is just organizing
around hardened positions
these empathetic triggers i love this
notion of uh
pattern curators so leaders of the
future are going to
be pattern curators guys mark that down
you'll be hearing and thinking about
that for some time to come here we call
them influencers a little bit content
curators
information is everywhere if it's
everywhere it's about low value the
value in the future is curation
and bringing things together in a way
that that resonates
with people so there's resonance right
there's resonance
in the maga tribe the red insurgency uh
there's resonance in the blm
antifa you know left wing sort of
radical anti-racist
uh tribe and these tribes now are
hardening
and the system is mutating in a way
that's making the
any cross-tribal collaboration more
difficult uh
it's they're setting up hard barriers
for us to transmit information and
whatnot and so all this is escalating
it's escalating and we're leading into
election here in 2020
we'll talk about this who the hell knows
what's going to happen
who the hell knows what's going to
happen but we can continue to look at
the system
that's producing these outcomes and
one of the things that you wanted to
talk about today that i would love to
hear about is
potential coup triggers or mechanisms
like
how and are these networked tribes
going to battle each other uh given that
really the
election is just but yet a waypoint on
this long journey
it is not the final destination it's
it's a skirmish
within the greater war um how
is this going to play out now that we
know people are hardened their brains
have been
rewired to match these pattern of
empathy
we know who the evil empire is whatever
side you're on the other side are the
evil guys
there's no empathy to the out group
empathy only to the in group
social media has been hijacked and
corrupted by the
establishment people who want to control
what you see and what you hear and what
you think about
and now we're leading up into a point
where we're going to vote
on something that's going to have some
impact but again not the end of the
story
so what is going to happen why did you
want to talk about
coup triggers or mechanics
and what are you seeing what what has
got your attention about that right now
i mean of course we have election a
couple weeks away but but what what is
what is relevant about that topic to you
right now well it's you know
brought up a lot you know mostly as a
kind of a scare word
um yeah you know people are okay the
people on the left are saying a
trump may attempt a coup if
uh the election is close and he claims
fraud
and the people on the right are saying
that uh no matter what the outcome
people on the left in the military and
the in the you know the deep state or
whatever is
or planning a coup to get him out of
office
uh based on the same kind of thing and
and there's planning on
i think maybe more of the planning and
i've seen you know what's
being talked about on both sides is that
it's more on the left actually
because i could see it actually
operating inside the government
you know and other things how to remove
trump if the
it refuses to go and what constitutes
refuses to go i don't know
but most people have this kind of fuzzy
notion of
what a coup is and how it works and i
wrote a report a couple years ago
based on ludwig's book and and other
stuff
uh and you know the idea of a coup
is actually you know most mostly what we
think about when we
you know conjure it up is this uh
third world country you know generals
take charge
um that kind of you know gives us a kind
of an image in our head
you know what it basically is is that
somebody gets in front of the government
machinery in front of the you know
top-down
uh hierarchy of the bureaucracy
both you know corporate and government
and then
issues you know seizes control of the
ability to issue orders and tells
everybody
what to do and it just flows down
through the bureaucracy uh they came out
of the
the colonial period um during the 60s
is that you know the colonial
governments uh were
divorced from the will of the people
obviously they were externally opposed
imposed on the people and they were used
to doing you know just exercising orders
taking orders from the governor do this
do that
they would do it so all you really
needed to do
is cease control and you know this
colonial government became the
government
of say this new nation because
all the competence was in the
bureaucrats that had been trained by the
the previous colonial owners
is that they were still used to taking
orders so all you had to do was seize
control of the
of of the government agencies and issue
orders
and it would just fall into line um and
since the media was so centralized
you know all you have to do is get the
hold of the the tv stations and the
radio and
and it broadcast it out you're in
control
um then there were a lot of like ins and
outs you know insider baseball and how
to
tactically kind of manipulate that and
what should you seize first
so you get to the united states in in
the current environment in the current
internet environment
and you look at the bureaucracy of
government and how it
operates in the size of the country and
the diversity of media and everything
else
and there isn't any central point i mean
there's no place
that you could be uh
to kind of issue orders and have the
thing obey you
right there's no machinery anymore it's
like it's
too decentralized too big too too
complex to to kind of dictate that so
a standard coup um is impossible it's
impossible in a
in a complex government plus the people
involved in you know in
all these bureaucracies whether
corporate or government are you know
um too smart they won't obey a
an enough order they're not used to
taking orders that go outside of a
certain
realm so you know if trump tried a coup
or somebody else tried to cou on
trump that would just not fly more than
12 hours
and they would be in guantanamo before
you even noticed i mean
it's just not a possible thing it's not
doable
um now what what is possible in terms of
seizure of power is what's going on you
know we saw the kind of
you know example of censorship going on
in the corporate realm
is that um what can happen on the
network is it routes around government
power runs around government
legal restrictions they can do things to
you as an individual that you could
you know the government can't do i
couldn't even think of doing
so all of our constitutional protections
are against you know
you know preventing the state from
encroaching on our freedoms
uh what we're looking at is now that the
network
corporate and individual these open
source networks are are
really the power source they can
determine whether you can work or not
they can determine whether you have
access to transaction systems they have
all the things that networks touch they
can they can
dictate whether you get access to them
or not and
networks touch everything though i mean
even dating even job searching uh
even um yeah everything
if you're banned from these platforms
and once this thing starts to you know
ban you you're you're basically a
non-citizen i mean you could you could
go off and
you know do a solo farm out in the woods
if you can get the
afford the property but you have to go
through the finance to get the buy it
and
and and other things it's just not uh
yeah you could be disconnected entirely
so a soft coup
is a different story uh something that
you know takes control
of society uh dictates
how things work takes control of
government bureaucracies takes control
of corporate bureaucracies
uh puts them gets them all into what i
call alignment and that
that's possible but a hard coup no
it's just fantasy um just like the way
people describe fascism it's
the way they describe it with jack boots
and militarism you could find that in
you know communist russia too it is or
soviet union
i mean they were militaristic they spent
30 of their budget on the military
i mean it's like you know
all of the things that they described
that kind of surface level of fascism
isn't really fascism
fascism is something else it's a system
right
it's a state of mind john well yeah but
i'm just kidding making a joke about
antifa and idea and all that
yeah but it's one of the three big
systems of the 20th century they fought
it out
that's right so what makes it a system
people aren't addressing it's not
because
they were uniforms or thuggish rights
like there's there's a system dynamic
that's important in terms of that
making them competitive right and a flaw
that caused them to get beat
so quickly indeed so a hard
coup i think much like a 1860
civil war notion are pretty much ruled
out
right yeah it's just not the way the
world works
um would you say that the power of the
federal government
relative to the power of the other
forces in our lives is
relatively diminished versus where it
was say at the founding
let's say right and so where would this
be part of the
post post-westphalian world where the
the network power
uh the tribes that form around ideas
and causes and and even just gangs
straight-up gangs
that these are all forces that are just
sort of superseding and even tearing
apart sort of the notion of the
nation-state
structure is this evidence of that same
process unfolding
yeah i mean for most of the history of
the united states the
the federal government really wasn't
much of a factor right so
i mean it was small it wasn't funded
that much it didn't have like
much of a role in our lives on a day to
day it was mostly done at the state
level and even then it really was down
really down to the community that does
most of the heavy lifting
you know the county or the town that you
live in and um
but the general arc across the western
world across the whole world
was that the nation state this
collection of bureaucracies run
usually by a constitution or some kind
of founding document
and some mechanism for replacing the
leadership structure usually a
market-based mechanism
what went out was getting bigger and
more comprehensive and more powerful
over time
and the driving force for that was
warfare right and so we saw the kind of
apex of that during the cold wars these
two monstrous
you know states and the systems that
they developed were built for
waging total war against each other
for an indefinite period of time and
world war ii you know showed that
bureaucracies could could mobilize
everything uh
the surprise of world war one uh you
know just as a side
an aside is that was that the state was
better at mobilizing than they
anticipated
and it mobilized so fast and so you know
to such a degree
that they got caught in their own in
their own uh um
success is that they ground each other
up they didn't anticipate that being
so quick they were thinking more 1870 i
mobilized quickly i
take the enemy's capital was all over so
uh okay so
here's the thing we get nuclear weapons
which prevents
large-scale conventional weapons or
conventional warfare from happening we
don't get world war three
we don't get world war iv uh the big
large-scale conventional war between the
major powers
becomes a thing of the past we have
guerrilla wars then we
kind of come down to one system that's
mostly you know capitalist democratic
democratic capitalism um and uh
there's no opposition there's really not
anyone to fight against
and uh the nation starts to crumble it
you know
assaulted by globalization insulted by
the internet lack of control over its
borders i can control over its media
message
lacking control over its people flows uh
it
inability to control its finances its
economy or its economic fortunes
all of that starts to dissipate the
nation state okay so the nation states
gets weaker and we get into the you know
21st century and we see the uh
you know it uh it is kind of uh
bequeathing corporations with a lot of
the powers that they would have normally
assumed themselves
to kind of solve the problems of of you
know what's the limits on speech
um how does it you know what how do
we determine who gets access and who
doesn't and how that all works
uh how the economy is organized it just
like let them figure it out
um and corporations have been taking
advantage of that they'd be getting you
know
bigger and more powerful and the people
who run them get wealthier and wealthier
and the system has underperformed as a
result in terms of you know
providing results to everybody so uh
yeah corporations are a lot stronger
than they have been in the past um
i wrote few reports on that is that you
know we we don't pass a law
saying uh that we should ban guns we let
companies
decide that they want to ban guns by
preventing finance
of of companies that make or sell guns
or
you know you can't buy a gun because the
transaction system starts to break down
and
starts to ban you from doing that i mean
and the noose gets
tighter and tighter on that system um
and eventually if left alone it probably
would
result in the you know total elimination
of that comfort commercial
conversion element of gun ownership and
purchasing
what what's interesting to consider
we've talked about this before is the
notion of alignment
among networks and so right now there's
an alignment among black lives matter
antifa radical left and the corporations
which is
the interesting part and uh in talking
to matt stoller who's a democrat but
anti-trust
focused and he truly believes that we
need to be taking strong action
against these monopolies and social
media and information space
what happened yesterday with the hunter
biden thing is is just like
an extreme example of why there does
need to be some sort of
involvement here anti-trust involvement
excuse me and what it shows though is
that the alignment
is that blm antifa and the corporations
have one thing in common which is they
want to see the diminishment of the
power of the federal government
slash and or the corporations want to
co-opt the federal government
into doing its bidding or at least just
keeping them aside
so to allow them to continue on and
doing the work that they're doing
with being unmolested by the federal
government trying to protect its
citizens
uh from things like you know information
control and being like zeroed off the
grid and being unable
to participate you know poor laura well
poor laura luma laura loomer gets banned
from twitter and then she runs for
office and she's actually wins the
primary still isn't back on twitter
we had uh the press secretary's twitter
account yesterday get shut down for a
minute we had jackpot sobek's account of
a million plus
gets shut down for a little bit uh and
clearly
the ban of like posting an article from
new york new york post
is evidence of the power of social media
they have in controlling these
empathetic triggers the information that
we have that creates these tribes
and creates the dissonance and the and
the the conflict that we have today
um you we we've established that the an
old school
coup is out of the question one thing we
didn't exactly mention too is that the
government itself is divided
so even if there was one place where you
could issue an order
you know half the people in the
government are with trump half the
people who
aren't and it's uh it is in of itself a
place of conflict
um but i think that we've seen in
talking to folks like dr darren beatty
and others that the democrats have in
place a plan to affect
a coup in a way that's non-traditional
uh but yet in a way that we've seen in
uh
rolled out in other countries around the
world which would be
you know mass protests mobilized in the
street information
campaign law fair election uh voting you
know maybe tampering
or just drawing uh doubt or confusion to
the election results and then litigating
as best as possible and just
basically an all-out assault on all the
various elements
of the election the legitimacy of the
election
creating the image of mass uprising in
the street
with people burning stuff looting
terrorizing folks
and whatnot um it has been effective in
other countries to get the outcome that
the people
desired you know of a color revolution
do you think that something like that a
do you think that that is a reasonable
position to take that the democrats are
potentially rolling out their
uh color revolution playbook in the
united states a do you think that's a
reasonable position to take and b do you
think
this irrespective of that if they these
things are happening
uh are they going to be effective or
powerful is there
is there a way that with a marginal like
an accurate marginal trump victory
that this this this method of color
revolution actually can invalidate that
or
at least prevent trump from maintaining
power etc
okay um i don't think the uh
democratic politicians are capable of
actually leading anything
close to that uh any more than
the republicans are able to lead the
trump insurgency it's like it's got a
life of its own it's got its own
own designs and own needs and and
there's millions of people
participating out in the network
they can ride it they can take advantage
of it they can they can
feed it uh but uh ultimately they don't
control it
you know one thing about anything open
source is that leadership is contingent
right
is that it's only cont it's contingent
on you moving it forward
if you don't move it forward you're
forgotten i mean there's no
there's no loyalty to in that regard
you're kind of pushed out of the way
immediately people just stop listening
to you
so um what we're seeing on the
on the tribes of the left is that they
formed first largely because there was
like an existential threat from
copenhagen threat from trump
um that combined to create these
patterns that had vibrance
what you do online is you start building
these patterns and they have no limits
they get bigger and bigger and bigger
and bigger and they take more and more
people
are curating pushing them forward and
they're expanding and they're applying
them to it
you know that kind of consolidation just
continues to grow
uh expansion um and we haven't seen the
limits of these what these the tribal
networks are going to end up
becoming um and uh
what they do regardless of who's in who
wins the election is they're going to
continue to expand
and how they expand is they
go for alignment and we see this
to a certain extent in china which is
running a network strategy towards
you know governance it got even got its
own gamified version
of of kind of network
compliance using the what they call the
uh social credit system
right that kind of rewards you you know
based on your compliance with
what the network wants um
alignment is uh based on something out
of uh you know fashion's history called
gleck shalton
this is everyone in phase meaning
everybody
who participates in the government in
every organization
has to believe the same thing and if you
don't
you're out in this case the patterns
that are being curated are huge
i mean they're massive and they're
sprawling and they um
you know it's all identifying what they
consider bad behavior
evil behavior and they're going from
company to company to company
forcing them to align align their hr
align their
corporate outlook and they get adherence
inside the government
you know they don't go through the top
per se like the traditional kind of
political
mechanism you put a political appointee
running running an agency
is that they go sideways into the into
the agency and you start getting
individuals that flip
and they become advocates for the
pattern advocates for the tribe
um and they call attention they become
whistleblowers and pop things up
we see this on you know the tribes of
the right and then the tribes of the
left where they kind of
throw up some information to show hey
you know this is what's happening
um and get you know get policies changed
and get and get things
get things moving towards the tribal
goals so uh
this alignment keeps on going to the
point where
in in network terms everything is the
same you know
once you get up to a certain level of a
certain size
the network effects are so powerful it
overwhelms everything else
it's kind of a tipping point this is why
we have that's why facebook is a kind of
a natural monopoly of sorts right
and twitter is that if you try to create
your own you're never going to be able
to get up to that
size because it's you know in the same
space because they have a natural
monopoly to do that network effect
because you can already find everybody
on there and there's so much information
it's
and it is you know so much history of
information on that platform that is
that it's just impossible to be um
it you know exudes its own gravity
and in it uh in the case of alignment is
that uh
you know you're seeing this coercion
occur and uh
there's a little thing that i call that
i saw this in the iraq war too
is that there's a kind of a financial
feedback loop that forms
um i call that a bizarre violence in the
past where they in
in iraq they had ied manufacturers and
placers and spotters and everyone else
selling their services and they get paid
for it
and you know that all this expertise
started flowing around in a market
formation
in the case of these these patterns is
the people who you know teach the stuff
and who you know uh there's money that's
you know given by corporations to
the bigger groups inside these tribal
networks uh millions of dollars and
there's investment
massive investment in different centers
and uh
you know advertising and support so
there's brands that develop
um you know even the worth of you know
how much is the blm brand worth right
now it's worth a lot
it's worth a lot of money uh it has you
know
value uh and it generates uh
donations it has you know demand
on the side of companies so um
yeah so you have this financial feedback
loop you have the alignment
and you have the network effects and
that becomes
a basis for a kind of totalitarianism
and um you know once
once it gets too far there's really not
anything to stop it there's no
you know terms of service replace the
constitutional protections
right so we have the bill of rights well
that's protect us against the government
but when it comes to you know protecting
us against
everything else which is everything else
right now
virtually everything that you interact
with i don't interact with the
government barely ever
i mean you don't either and and
everything really is just
this networked world um well the terms
of service are really
what protects you and we have no control
over that that's all
dictated by uh
the companies and uh the groups that are
forcing them into alignment
and those are going to determine your
future sounds to me like the soft coup
has already happened and it's not
one president or the other it's just the
government the federal government gone
and the real power that are controlling
what are outside of that and they've
they've they've stolen that
that power and until or unless
somebody uh in the federal level decides
to do something about it it's only going
to get worse the republicans have had
three and a half sorry 3.9 years
now to actually do something about this
issue and they have not
and they are getting to the point now
where i bet they're thinking to
themselves man i sure as hell wish
we would have done something in the past
as they're staring down the polls which
say
that many of the republicans are about
ready to get slaughtered including the
president even though i don't
necessarily believe the polls at this
time
uh so it's not just the republic it's
not just
it's the uniparty which is not taking
the action here
and i think it's a combination of
ignorance
they just have no idea the power of
what's really happening
uh and then of course they're corrupted
and they have money behind them
and they're paid to look the other way
uh all this stuff this hemming and
hawing about section 230 and
freedom of speech and censorship and
whatever it's all just talk
nothing's happening there's no pro
there's no there's no outcome there's no
new protections
yeah they're worried about the supreme
court stuff i was like who cares
i mean truly that slow slow system
of of determining what's the government
can do or not that's like
wow that's so 20th century it's like
this stuff is moving fast
and it has a direct impact on our lives
that surrender court doesn't really
impact us barely at all
right right and even even if it was a
life cycle and that is five
ten years or something whereas they
could have made changes immediately that
would have had immediate impact and
would protected us
and what's scary and we're going to get
to this is the tribal totalitarianism
and the long night but
you know what's scary is that with it
almost
the the horse is almost like totally out
of the barn at this point right it's
like there's there's no
bringing it back without drastic action
and no one
seems to be willing to take the steps do
you think it's ignorance do you think
it's malfeasance do you think it's
corruption
what what is it or they just don't care
like i don't know
yeah i mean you know the descent
function
is is kind of like a republican feature
or the
tribes of the right should be more on
the descent side
they never really were a funny thing
about us
the us right is it's very different than
what people
think you know the famous tom wolf quote
you know fascism is always about to fall
on the u.s but it
always falls on europe instead is
because of the the right in the us is
all about
leave me alone i mean you know just
don't put any restrictions on me let me
do my own thing and that's like the
whole almost the whole of the us history
it's like these thousands of communities
running their own show
um and that ended you know going into
world war ii and becoming a you know
a state capable of universal
mobilization it's
it's um yeah it's a
the um oh i forgot what the point wasn't
going to make it
if there's a million things to go down
here i mean what
what happens where do we go what what do
these network tribes do
i mean we we talked about coup mechanics
and we see that the old way of doing
things is not going to work what's the
new way
what and civil war mechanism like let's
get into those subjects here
okay so the right at least in my view
was uh
best suited to try to run the descent
try to keep the channels of
communication open
um and it hasn't done a good job of that
right
uh and you know it's in a consensus
descent dynamic which is really the left
and the right is the consensus forms
it becomes very powerful for a short
period of time the descent keeps it
in check and then when it becomes
useless it becomes you know
it doesn't apply anymore the sense
supposed to take it apart
and wipe it out and eradicate and get it
to move away
um so that's a nice stable dynamic
so that didn't really happen um now we
see kind of emergence of tribes on the
right
using some of the same dynamic that we
see on the left
and they haven't been as active because
trump has been
in place my theory is that trump makes
people feel
on the right makes people feel a little
you know a bit safe
in that regard that they're not going to
be encroached upon by the left
if if the left was really encroaching
upon them they would you know trump
would be gone
right you know but as long as he's there
it's kind of evidence that they can
continue to live their lives and do
whatever they want um
but once he's gone i think that dynamic
is going to change really really quickly
is that they're they're gonna start to
see this kind of encroachment everywhere
um and that they'll panic and they'll
tribalize and the tribalization
usually i mean i picked out a few that i
saw emerging it's mostly like the
anti-bias
thing uh you know in the workplace where
people are
trying to apply a lot of these uh
anti-racism
patterns on the workplace uh
the uh kind of anti-anarchist
anti-traitor kind of approach
to protesting the streets of the
anti-fascists and their ant
against the police and and how that is
uh
disruptive and that will become a
pattern that people can say okay
these people are doing this they should
be
excluded from society kind of thing um
but you know i just don't see that
developing
yet or i haven't seen you know there was
a little bit of an attempt to do that
last month but it was too little too
late for the republican party to
get or the republicans to kind of get
that going um
kind of get that tribal dynamic going
will it happen after trump
perhaps perhaps not because uh the thing
is is if this
tribes of the left keep on advancing and
they advance fast enough after the
election
is that they can deny access to the
right to prevent it from tribalizing
um it's a race so if they move quickly
and they identify everything that the
right is tribalizing on
you know the patterns that they're
curating uh they can wipe them out
before they even get going
and then then it's just a fade to
complete it's like you know if all the
podcasts that you're on and you're
interacting all the people that you
interact with online
well what if they're all gone no
what if they're not online i mean
twitter loses a little bit facebook
loses a little bit but it really doesn't
make any difference
or they're on and that but their their
reach declines because they're
being muted and the ais are working
against them and
their their messages don't get out um
and if they do get out they look like
it's just fake it just it goes like
three stops and
it dies so you don't even know you're
being
manipulated um so uh yeah
there's a potential of happening well
before the right tribalizes to the point
where it could actually put a
stop to this there's a lot of scary
things going on right there i'm gonna
go in reverse order a little bit one i
definitely understand the need to be
able to organize
outside of typical social media avenues
we have to have private networks because
ultimately one day if you are on the
wrong side of things you are going to
get zapped and silenced right off the
network not able to reach out and
connect to people not able to see the
patterns that you're interested in
seeing
not able to connect with like-minded
people or find empathy of any kind
anywhere at any time you will be
completely and totally isolated
like you may have been 200 years ago and
so we in the liminal order identified
that as an issue a couple of years ago
so we have worked very
diligently to build a network outside of
the social media network
outside of youtube outside of twitter
outside of any of it once you're in the
liminal order we have our own private
system our own private communication
network our own methods of distributing
information our own sense making
capabilities
our own synthesis that we we take and
our own sort of recommendations to the
membership about how
to best proceed in an optimal way uh in
in the current environment whether it be
covet or the riots or the election or
the economy
it's a positive tribe though yeah we're
better together because and then here's
the reason why we
band together and that uh you know it
provides you that kind of uh you know
in this environment you're only a smart
and you're only as safe as your network
right and if you have a network around
you and protecting you and
helping you filter this information
you're you're better off
um but it's it's different than these
big pattern matching networks these big
you know blobs yeah those things act
they're mindless
they just act right and act right right
right they have their own animation
right our
our animation is to like protect and to
be positive while the emergent tribal
networks are just
they have their own animation their own
energy that just happens through
uh emergence and one thing that's that's
you said that made me
think of my my old gen x day he's in
college was studying cold war
and studying uh the arms race right and
and studying
how it was a race to have dominance
uh in a you know obviously existential
mission critical circumstance of
who can destroy the planet first uh and
and that that uh
really shaped so much of the economics
and and
and politics and culture of the time it
sounds
i'm hearing echoes of an arms race right
now
where the first one across the finish
line
is the one that's going to have
dominance
whereas in the cold war we settled into
mutually assured destruction
which was a balance uh and it's still
balanced today by the way all those
nukes are still around and they're all
still pointed at all of us but nobody
really seems to think about it too much
anymore
but this race seems to be a winner take
all
race is that is that right john like
if they take if one network tribe takes
over
if they if they can craft the ais in a
way that they want
if they have alignment with the
corporations
if they can affect the most you know
powerful pattern matching and empathy
curation
and they can silence people they can cut
you off from finance cut you off from
the network ruin your reputation for
life
pin the worst crap you ever did in your
life the first results for your name
on google like is this a winner take all
race john yeah
that's that's my worry is that network
effects
means that it's a winner tickle yeah and
and that uh
yeah the uh once it reaches a certain
point it's going to be kind of a fade
accompli it's just
there's no way to fight against it
you're fighting against everything
and you're fighting alone and uh
you know even though even the little
network you're you know you're running
your own
network but you know you still have to
have hosting and you still have to have
some kind of transaction processing you
still have to have some kind of
you know infrastructure that supports
you well if that's all denied
if you're treated like a fortune or like
a like a
uh wikileaks you can just be wiped off
platform
after platform yeah and then it's
eventually just kind of
die off um disappear
the uh the question is whether it goes
you know global i mean we see it as a
nationalist approaches
with china they have like this one
pattern that they're curating and
they're trying to
expand their influences globally by
getting countries and individuals to
align even sports stars like aligning i
won't criticize you on this and this
it's crazy but they look at every little
instance
as as a champ you know anyone who's
commenting on china has to say the right
thing
um can this can this network inside the
united states extend beyond
the u.s i don't know i think it has
potential to do that
is that they're you know it it could
become
kind of a global blop and then
it locks everybody into this one view of
the world
and that anything that deviates in any
bit of this pattern is like
immediately attacked and disconnected
and the
people involved are destroyed uh this
kind of orthodoxy of thought based on
this kind of you know
ad hoc pattern that was based on crappy
theory that
like a historical and it's like rewrites
history and rewrites the world and it
rewrites you know
human relations and it and it locks
everything in and and
you know most of the responses i get
from people who like
want to reject that say oh let's smash
the network and everything else well no
it's not going to happen um
and that you know living outside of the
network's influence is going to be easy
and it's not
it's everywhere it's if you want to make
money and you want to enjoy it or you
want to
you know live a normal life you have to
be connected to this network
um putting it along let's look at in the
long view is that um
marshall mcluhan that media philosopher
i like so much is like
he uh he thought that the only way out
of this
is to craft a social artifact a
technological artifact
that kind of runs you know kind of a
overarching infrastructure for society
that's
that we can purposely control and write
in protections and
and and do the things that you know
set in the limits as to how it operates
and do it in a way that's
intelligent kind of like the
constitution but for the network
um and that a lot of that heavy lifting
is going to be done through ais and just
like it or not the biggest ais in the
world are on the social networks
they interact with three and a half
billion people on facebook alone and so
like every day
they you know they can monitor
conversations down to the individual
level
uh voice and and text
they can filter it they can they can
filter in real time
uh you know as you're uploading the
picture or as you're making the comment
it will decide whether or not it's valid
or not before it even happens
before it even hits the network so and
it can do it with everyone
all three and a half billion all at once
so um
ais are the you know the mechanism now
do we develop a
a system that uh is looser that that
protects the individual
and their ability to make decisions on
their own and and uh
kind of a network bill of rights so to
speak i mean that allows you to own data
allows you to you know operate as
a free individual or um do we allow uh
the
the as to lock down as one view of the
world
uh you know it's like thinking about how
how minds develop
coherence uh is that
you know do you develop a system that
where lots of different ideas can
can merge together to create a new new
thought
uh new idea or do you like
have so much discipline that everything
is just one idea
you know one way of thinking and that
anything that merges in your head that
that is contrary to that you stomp it
down
i mean i like the more fluid approach i
like to be able to
you know adapt to new information and i
think that's long term
is the only way of society is is to be
able to be as loose as possible
but not too loose it's like you know how
do you deal with the the 20th century is
that you want as much
freedom of movement of the individuals
and freeman freedom of ideas and
expression
as possible as you could stand but not
too much too much is chaos
too much is revolution too much is
everything falls apart
but you need it in order to adapt and do
things that the
kind of top-down bureaucracies and
infrastructures
can do in the communist world so um
yeah how do you balance that i think a
lot of the fight we're seeing right now
is over that who gets to set the
standards for those ais who builds that
technological artifact who sets it you
know
it's like this little debate um over um
what gets censored yeah you know do we
say that every anonymous source
coming out of the media is now a
disreputable source or
if anything that's like leaked is a hack
like that the
trump taxes obviously they were they're
hacked in
and loses you know use of the term um
should those be disallowed should those
that all that discussion been blocked on
social media
so um well what you're seeing we're
seeing is that the people in charge of
the ais who are
curating the content deciding what the
rules are are the corporations like
facebook twitter and google and we know
for a fact that the google and twitter
and facebook
are staffed by people on the left
they're staffed by former democratic
committee members they're staffed by
people
who cried when trump lost they're
staffed by people top to bottom
who think that people on the right are
racist and evil in nazis and they need
to be silenced and there's no
empathy there's no love there's no
acceptance there's no kindness
they're the evil evil enemy and they
must be stopped and we have these tools
the social media companies
that where i think they believe that
they know that they have an opportunity
now to do exactly what we're talking
about
set the set the rules uh you know if you
can't win the war of ideas then just
change the battlefield change the rules
change the terrain
and that's what they're doing in real
time we're seeing it happen and
with the selectivity of what's
permissible what isn't what's leaked
what's hacked it's all
you know it doesn't matter it's all just
for show we know what it is
anything bad against democrats bad hack
banned anything bad against trump
russia collusion you know the the the
hoax the whole hoax were all these years
all this information all these bs
dossiers and all this leaking and
circular laundering of information that
happened through the fbi
and cnn and all these things all that's
okay
we've seen that that's okay we can do
that democrats can do that people on the
right cannot do that so we're facing
truly a race that could be winner take
all and right now there's no one from
the government doing anything to protect
people on the right much less just
americans in general from being
subjected to this
and again a guy like matt stoller i
think should be listened to much more
clearly these days because he is totally
on point when it comes to this and he's
a democrat
and he doesn't approve of the way that
you know sort of things are shaking out
he certainly sees the power and the
problem
of the monopolies of the tech monopolies
i'm having a loom bukari on from
breitbart in a couple of weeks
he's written a book recently revealing
all of what's happening called deleted
i talked to him a couple years ago he's
been on this beat for a number of years
tracking what google and facebook and
twitter and reddit and all these people
are doing
uh as a way to just squash us all stuff
us down into a little hole
bury us with dirt and just pretend that
thing never happened and gosh darn it
you know we had it coming because we're
evil people we're evil racists
now one of the things that you mentioned
earlier which i was happy that you
mentioned and i did want to talk about
briefly
and while trump's actions may have not
been timely nor decisive they are at
least a step in the right direction
in that he's trying to disrupt the
pattern mechanism
mechanism system out there or introduce
new patterns
that people can latch on to and
empathize with and identify with
you mention the anti-anarchy tribe so
that would be sort of triggering a tribe
around
law people law and order people that
don't want to see buildings burned down
the fires etc
and so trump has taken some action to
sort of create that
that tribe uh and then we talked about
the anti-indoctrination tribe
uh which i think kind of ties in with
the anti-bias tribe as well which is
just sort of
uh fighting back against the 1619
project creating 1776
thing yeah fighting against critical
race theory in the federal government
the bias trainings implicit association
tests uh you know sit with your
whiteness courageous conversations
nonsense
that's happening everywhere and i'll
tell you i've seen the influence of this
already
once trump and you know kudos also to
christopher ruffo who was on the show a
couple weeks ago
kudos to them for actually putting this
out there and saying look critical race
theory is a bad thing
here's why even though he fumbled it
totally in the debate uh but here's why
and i'm now seeing we're getting reports
from suburban moms
all over the country who who who did not
see themselves as part of this culture
war
probably voted for uh hillary uh did not
think about voting for trump
where now because this idea is in their
head they're now seeing it in their
schools
right now they're not seeing it
happening and then they're rallying
right and that's going to zoom after the
election if bite gets in and
you know it's just it's going to be the
the existential fear
is going to really kick in and people
are going to start to look at this and
and
those tribes are going to form around
these patterns and they're going to try
to root it out at the community level
and root it out at the national level
um and you have already have the some of
the curators already in place like
you know roofo and others who are like
constantly out there
uh you know finding examples um
and you just you see the pickup but the
thing is trump
is not knowledgeable in this stuff and
he's not he didn't really
catch catch on to how it should be
framed and um you know it's uh
you know it could be different uh you
know four years from now assuming that
we
don't go all the way towards a
totalitarian outcome it's that we have a
another election and um you know
somebody who can actually articulate
those
those tribal needs comes out i think
like a tucker carlson's probably the guy
who
i picked out a couple years ago or
whatever who has who who can really
feel that you know this tribal kind of
sentiment developing
um you know in terms of what can be done
at the stoler idea about breaking up the
big
monopolies i don't see that as valuable
uh you know
i'd rather see i mean here's here's the
thing
we're not just involved in this kind of
problem domestically
this is a kind of a global contest
between
you know systems between china and the
u.s the u.s system
and if you look at the map of you know
our social networks which are gathering
all the data that's needed to train all
the ais for all the products of the
future
right it's we encircle china
and russia you know those that are kind
of like islands
in this kind of blue sea of of social
networks that
our u.s nominally us controlled
so uh if we can conti keep that intact
that three and a half billion on you
know
that facebook has still growing at a
couple hundred thousand a day kind of
thing
it's a that gives us incredible leverage
going forward if we can get it right
and get it propagated of course it could
be incredible leverage growth
things go wrong if they start to you
know train the ais and they
they roll out globally but um
you know systemically we got to do that
in order to keep our products and
services
cutting edge and above everybody else's
yeah
it's wealth it's wealth well let me
places like europe
you know we put all the data
restrictions on you know put all the
restrictions on the social networks
uh kind of hobble them put their heads
in the sand ostrich like and
and they are basically hobbling all
their products and services going
forward
oh i see right i mean what are you gonna
develop i mean you don't have any data
you can't use the data that
you you're collecting and then here
comes the us and here comes china and we
got tons of data from everywhere in the
world
and we got a product and ai and that are
trained on that data are going to be in
everything it's going to be
i mean you're already seeing it just
creep in it's in cars right
it's in it's in all the services that we
get online it's in dating it's in
uh job hunting it's in um
you know every physical product is going
to have a network component i just put a
new
oven in and it has you know smart
network features in it
so um yeah yeah i'm not as optimistic
about
the united states as social media and
data collection
being a positive force in the world i
see more alignment between
the google folks and china than i do
with them and myself
and the people that write the algorithms
he who control the algorithm
control the universe i'm getting some
dune vibes here on that i mean the
algorithms
are really going to subtly just guide
you down
the dead-end path if they want you to go
down there where you don't see anything
new and you don't get anything new and
you have no access
but if you're one of the chosen people
based on your data based on your
connections your
your your communication heat map like
who do you follow what tweet did you
like
you know what did you buy a gun you know
you get funneled this way or funneled
that way those algorithms aren't really
like um
i mean they're they're ai really it's
just it's just it takes these patterns
and it
kind of you know it learns from that
and then it acts on that and those ais
are
you know you know most people think of
ai as kind of like this human-like thing
you know human equivalent you know it's
a solitary
mind well that's just all science
fiction crap it's
when the ais are really taking off or
the ones that live in the social space
and they live in the space between us
they learn from what we say and what we
do and and
they're not human-like in that regard i
mean they're more like symbiotes
you know they're if we build them
correctly they're
they can help us grow faster and do more
things and and and
adapt quicker and be more successful
you know you know across the board right
but if we do a bad job with it if we try
to lock it down
it could be the worst dictatorship ever
i i feel
i feel like maybe we're on different
levels of optimism and pessimism here
john
from my perspective the people that
create the ais are already corrupted
with their
moral framework that sees me as the
enemy and it's already happening right
the the funnel is already happening the
the disconnection's already happening
john a couple a couple of months ago i
name-searched myself just to see where i
was in my google results and whatever
and literally zero from my website came
up under jack murphy live
nothing from jack murphy.com came up in
google search
so i get my uh my network guy who's been
doing seo and web stuff for
15 years to start taking a look and as
we're taking a look we keep hitting
search keep hitting search
keeping search we search bing everything
comes up in bing then we keep getting
searched on google and just like that
boom it was all back while we were
watching
while we were analyzing what was
happening and then about an hour later
there was articles from breitbart
federalists
you know all kinds of people saying hey
our google resource results were turned
off and now they're turned back on like
what's going on like
we are currently on a list i'm on a list
we're they're on
that just a trigger was hit a threshold
was hit something happened
they just whoosh they completely wiped
me out of the results
a hundred percent and so you know if you
ask me
i think the nefarious forces are already
at work and they're already on their way
to some sort of you know first across
the line
winner take all circumstance which is
right
terrible we're we're definitely in you
know guerrilla information war
right now and everyone's a participant
whether you want to be a participant
or not you're participating and
you know this it's for all the marbles i
mean who gets control of who writes
those ais who writes those algorithms
who writes who controls the network who
aligns it
do we have an open system or do we have
a lockdown system
and um it occurs every day you know
it's not going to be kind of this
guerrilla information war is not like
it's classic civil war you know we have
states that align with each other and
fight each other it's
this is a you'll see violence and we're
already seeing a little bit of violence
here and there and different
different city centers where either you
know people
uh going postal or you know
city centers being burned down but
that's all
the center of gravity the conflicts
online and all of that violence
is just to drive that online
conversation so when people are talking
about i'm going to do this
or that or you know they're out there
doing you know whatever
whatever in the street they're doing it
with
an eye to what how that will be
reflected online
and you notice how people are
interacting with taking videos and don't
take videos of me online or you know
while i'm doing this
uh constantly there's there's as many
people holding up their phones trying to
video
you know an event uh and share it online
as there are
actual participants you know doing stuff
so uh
nice sometimes i watch the kind of the
the experts on right extremism there are
almost as many experts on right
extremism as there are
right extremists i mean they're not
experts on
extremism they're experts that only
write extremism it's like nuts it's like
they don't understand history
at all you have to be across the board
yeah
well there's a lot of a historic
perspectives
out there right now it's like yeah it's
like the antifa it's like a
don't you i mean the anti-fascist
organization i mean if you go back in
history
i mean it started off as a as a
organization to protect the
groups on the left in the in the in the
late 20s in germany
and then it was banned after the
communist international in 1929 where
they
you know 30 people died and a bunch of
police died in a massive riot around
around that uh event and um that took
them off the
playing field they were bigger than the
small sa
and all the groups on the right were
tiny um in comparison one tenth the size
of of of the uh what they call the
front conference boon the front fighters
brotherhood
um you know with the fist and the whole
thing and then they when they were
formed in 1932 they were a stalinist
anti-fascist action uh with the flags
and the whole bit
the same thing that we see today uh they
were um
communist only they were stalinist only
they were controlled you know through
russian stalinism
and they took out most of their anger
and fought mostly with the groups on the
left
yeah i mean they were you know it was a
too little too late and and the sa and
the groups on the right grew as a result
of the chaos on that
so they don't people don't understand
how all this dynamic works and
why they're focusing exclusively on the
right i don't understand
yeah yeah well there's a lot of ignorant
people out there right now
they're not getting taught the things
they need the tea to be taught they're
receiving the patterns that match with
them they're filtering everything else
out
everybody feels morally justified in
what they're doing
uh i wonder and this is no need to
answer this but i just wonder one day if
we're going to be able to see
phys physiologically like uh or like
psychological profiles that
show who's susceptible to what type of
pattern and empathy triggers and
if there's like you can predict maybe
how people are going to separate oh yeah
that's already
right yeah that's the essence of micro
micro
marketing i mean that's the holy grail
it's harder to do than you think because
people
change right day by day yeah i mean
yeah we don't get like a physical
evolution the dna movement
and we have it for a long time it's very
slow yeah everything
the social is like going speed of heat
right and that network is even going
faster than it's evolving constantly
it's like
new data new information new ways of
organizing
it's constant evolution and how we fit
into that
yeah that's like trying to figure out
how to market a
specific product to a you know to a
specific individual is really tough
because it
changed the day change the hour it
changes
yeah it's like trying to hold you know
mercury in your hands and
or juggle mercury it's just like you
know these are the people i know who
have done that or tried to get down to
that level that's where you're at
there's no kind of target
that lasts any length of time it's just
yeah the revolution is just lightning
speed
the iteration is is faster people who
iterate their iteration machine
are going to be people that succeed in
the world today i think it was
i think it was jordan who first turned
me on to uh
that's what you gotta do you know you
gotta be your process of
of observing and adjusting and acting uh
faster and faster and in fact with a
heavy emphasis on just decide and act
side and act decide and act right so
that's what we try to do and i believe
that there's a lot of guys on the right
a lot of social media folks like myself
and others that
operate in that universe and decide and
act is certainly something that keeps
you ahead ahead of the game
the key i think the key to the ooda is
that orientation yeah
okay so okay the orientation is like you
know
it's observe orient decide act
um observation is like getting a lot of
good data in
and deciding and acting you know you can
you can do it quickly online
but orientation is everything you are
you're kind of gestalt
you know how you see the world and um
all your training
all your education all your family
upbringing everything goes into that
and if you have the right compass if you
have the right
direction it makes all the difference in
the world um
you know i from grand strategy all the
way down to the individual
is a like for instance in the 20th
century the u.s had
the right orientation its strategy its
execution was [ __ ]
throughout the entire thing right i mean
we're work
europeans always said we're incompetent
fools you know and
we didn't know anything about strategy
and they tore themselves in
a pardon wars twice and you know by the
end of the century we were
economically dominant the world hadn't
just been destroyed during the cold war
uh you know we know world war iii
nothing else i mean you know
somehow we bumbled through because we
had the right orientation we kept you
know
we allowed countries to make their own
decisions and get wealthy and
you know innovative and you know we kept
the whole thing together because we
were pointed in the right direction even
though our strategies and tactics
failed a lot of times we weren't really
that smart in that the same thing as
individuals is that
you can mess up a lot to be very
forgiving
uh if you if you have the right
orientation
i mean i do that with the kids you know
as the kids get older right they go to
college they go off into the world
and um they may get turned around a few
times
but if they're headed in the right
direction they end up coming back
right they get them you know they wipe
off the dust they get up off the ground
and they figure out
okay i got to go this way and i found
that
in my case as an individual you know
going through adversity i mean you get
beat up a few times or
the startup doesn't work or or it does
work and you're overwhelmed i mean if
you're pointed in the right direction
you can
you can figure it out yeah but um
yeah deciding and acting without that
orientation um
man if you're facing the wrong direction
like we were like say our grand strategy
after
2000 was uh still focused on global
policemen and
focus on the middle east and we iterated
in that direction and it was wrong it
was the wrong grand strategy it was like
you know we emphasized oil and we were
involved and we kept on iterating
iterating it
we were in afghanistan 17 years and no
results or 18 years
were uh messed up we spent billions on
on something that shouldn't have
happened
in iraq um so if you you know
facing the wrong direction you can
iterate all day
going in the wrong direction very true
very true and we could spend
um months and weeks years even talking
about the ooda loop and what it means
and where it came from and
how it's been implemented um one thing i
wanted to talk about before we get to
what's going to happen in november and
in january john which is something i
want to hear from you
right what what is the safest
social media and i have in my mind an
answer
when i say safest i mean the one
that is least likely to be
taken away from you co-opted controlled
is there a direct
maybe i'm i should just say it but i'm
thinking rss right like
is there a way to directly connect to
people and that's not going to be
uh censored or limited so long as you
have network access right
where is the role for rss moving forward
in this
universe today where these big platforms
have so much power
to me rss was like about and is about
today still and i still send the podcast
out on rss
is to me is like individual power is
that am i seeing that right is there is
there a place for this in the future
yeah i mean one of the companies i ran
boy back in 2001 published rss as an
open spec
so yeah we were trying to give the power
to people and allow them to
decide how they built their networks of
course that was co-opted by the facebook
and twitters
um rss is still there um
the you know clients for actually
consuming it
are less used that's the problem um
so uh it's always like a backup or a
fallback
for distributed or decentralized uh
social networking
all right um and
the problem is that a lot of the
platforms are things that we use like
phones
are extremely locked down so if a
an app that violates that kind of
general consensus
is developed you might not be able to
get it from the store might be able
might not be able to load it on your
phone um so that's the most like
restrictive is the phone
um and fewer fewer people have pcs
right general purpose computing um
and that's being restricted uh in terms
of platforms
i think uh the twitter
facebook and google google in terms of
youtube
will all be probably the last to flip
totally i mean they're being eroded
right now you'll see a lot more flipping
in the smaller platforms
putting into alignment but when they go
they'll all go at once
maybe the last one maybe facebook
um largely because it's trying it has to
navigate this globally
and there's lots of pressure and push
back on by you know all these different
governments globally and also it's uh
it's harder to see what's going on in
facebook because it's small community
focused
you're limited to 5 000 friends and most
of the conversations occur in those
smaller groups
and there's no really good overarching
mechanism to see everything that's going
on on the platform like you do in
youtube
and twitter so um it's not it's less of
a broadcast medium and it's harder for
external groups to enforce
um violations uh you know that's what
makes everyone so mad about the
tribes left mad about facebook is they
they they think there's something
horrible going on in there in those
little communities
you know people are communicating in a
way that they can't control and it
really just infuriates them
um can't see it it's got to be there
i mean it's got to be the reason why
people are not
conforming um so
that's my guess on that platform side is
that you know what do you think
i think rss and email lists are the
false
fallback solution for getting
information i consider myself like an
info
you know guerrilla information militia
you know our guys in the lo we work
independently we rise up to meet the
needs of the information
space in a time at which the federal
government and others
are failing to provide what we an
essential service so we're doing it
instead for ourselves much in the same
ethos as american patriotism and
militias
throughout all of our history and so we
constantly are thinking about you know
you know duplicate networks redundant
overlapping communication systems and so
we use you know stuff like this online
here but we also use email we also use
direct you know wordpress installations
we use rss distributions we use
third-party secure apps for
communication
what i want to see in the future for us
the liminal order within you know maybe
in 10 years
is to have built some sort of physical
infrastructure that that keeps us
in a way unreliant on ip addresses and
and
registrars and and service like that so
that we can truly be
uh protected and that is the end goal
there yeah i've seen
you know i was involved in all the kind
of resilient community stuff
i kind of coined the term brazilian
community back in 2007.
and it kind of took off it went big
right and so um
uh the effort to kind of build these
resilient these physical resilient
communities
uh kind of was uh
you know hard to implement right it's
like
people have their lives in their
different communities and it's hard to
get them all to
kind of come to the same location and uh
and agree on a lot more
than they were willing to agree on and
and trying to find the right fit i know
a lot of people go around trying you
know interviewing communities now
trying to find communities they can live
in um the idea of interviewing a
community is kind of a cool
concept uh but is there and then a
physical infrastructure uh
boy that's tough uh there may be
ways to do that using
you know uh blockchains and you build
the code into the blockchain and that
becomes like a corporate or
transactional infrastructure that that
serves as the backbone of the group
right it institutes its rules and
it institutes a kind of a transactional
framework
point system you know social status
you know adjudication all of that but i
mean i think that's the
maybe the the most valuable part of what
the blockchain was
i mean or could become i thought that
back in 2010 you know when we were first
looking at this thing at a dollar right
people were thinking storehouse of value
and i was like
oh granted we could speculate on
storehouse of value but the real thing
is like okay
i can i can build a corporate
infrastructure in this thing right
i could i could have it you could just
turn up off the street and then
follow the rules of this thing and be
rewarded
based on its you know successful
propagation how it works
i had an idea about building a company
where you would
uh gather metadata on every object in
the world
like pictures descriptions i mean like
you know this is a duncan like this is
the dunkin donuts
mug and you know of this time in this
time period
kind of a catalog of everything yeah
because the database has value over time
right
that was before the aei started training
and using these big
databases as kind of training
uh instruments for the bigger ones and
and
everybody would contribute and they
would be rated on it it would be
rewarded and anytime it's used
in a big ai the ai would have to pay a
royalty fee to
for however money that it makes or
whatever and then everybody
would be compensated over time as long
as this database existed
so you could be getting a royalty stream
you know
that would net maybe a hundred dollars
or 200 an hour
i was estimating over the first five to
ten years wow for every
hour you contributed to putting in no
matter who you were
and so that all the rules of that
company would be built into the
blockchain and i thought that was a
really cool idea
um and you could do the same with groups
but that takes a technical competence
that takes a
you know kind of a burden to get going
um
and if you did do it in the right way
you could create kind of an echo system
that kind of takes off
yep that runs separately that runs on
the kind of like this
mesh network that runs in the background
as you kind of you jailbreak
phones and those phones sir you know
kind of connect to each other
you have to have a certain density um
and uh to get them kind of communicate
but
it kind of goes sideways and it doesn't
go through the standard architecture
so as more bandwidth occurs at the
periphery then that becomes more and
more viable
yep uh but that's like still i mean i
keep on looking
for it just doesn't doesn't seem to
happen it's like
possible yeah well we're taking
incremental steps to get off the main
highway here and to take our own exit
and to create our own network in our own
enclosed environment with a wall a
barrier that we allow
you know what we want to allow to to
cross through the barrier or not
uh you know it's very much like concepts
we find in nature
systems design you know you don't want
to have everything everywhere touching
everyone all the time
so yeah yeah bad things happen to
everybody all at once we just saw that
happen with covet right
it was a reversal of the housing i mean
you know uh
you know prior to the reformation
onwards where
you know you had kind of communities and
that were built on
agreements and and general agreements is
like uh
most housing was was built with a wall
on the outside and facing inwards
towards the courtyard you see this in
italy you see this everywhere
across europe and then you started to
see these kind of calvinist communities
and these
you know protestant communities with
houses the face of the street
that didn't have bars on their windows
because the community was so
freaking strong that no one would come
into it
or no one inside the community was a
threat so we're kind of
going back to the older way to a certain
extent and then that
interior courtyard is where you have the
garden where you have the common space
uh it's a place to retreat yeah it's um
yeah it i don't know if you could do
that in a virtual way
i know in the physical way it's very
attractive if you have enough density of
people that want to move into that
that can be very cool um but you have to
have agreement on how to use that common
space
usually it was a family group extended
family yeah uh i think
also the muse set up in europe as well
too muse mews where they
all are facing into a common courtyard
uh and you know what destroyed that is
long-range connections and we all have
long-range connections right now from me
to hops to anybody anywhere in the whole
wide world for ideas
for viruses or you know for whatever
they can just close those two house down
and then you're isolated anyway so
uh it's a fascinating subject i'd love
to talk to you about it more maybe on a
different podcast because we're working
on this we're taking one step in
in in that direction as best we can just
get off the highway
build our own thing and then try to keep
iterating and moving in a direction
that's going to give us
true independence really because that's
we see all this coming john why do i see
it because i've been talking to you and
reading for you
for years and everything that you have
put out and all the things we've talked
about have come true
to fruition we see it happening you've
implanted a pattern
recognition system in my brain and i am
picking up on these things all over the
place
and that's why we keep talking and i
love it you've been a huge influence on
me whether you know it or not
also on the development of the liminal
order too uh and so i i really
appreciate uh
and and want to just thank you for that
sincerely because it's been thanks jack
you're doing a great job well i really
appreciate that coming from you that
means a lot
uh i want to get now to like the final
wrap-up
questions which are
what john is gonna happen november third
what's gonna happen between november 3rd
and january what happens after january
all right um we take
okay well just just this russian winner
that's the opponent in this election you
know biden sat it out
right and just let the covet do its work
and the guerrillas pick apart trump and
and it's just
driving towards the inevitable
conclusions retreat from moscow it's
like
okay november 3rd he's out the system is
was geared up to kind of push him out
all the media everyone all the
bureaucracies are pretty much aligned in
that regard
i want to allow a repeat of it to occur
um so what happens well you have
a very very very weak candidate in biden
a weak president
um and you get you know a very
aggressive
vice president but that really doesn't
matter so much is that the network
tribes on the left will
eat them for lunch and that
he'll do whatever you want or you know
he can to appease him
he won't be able to oppose him much and
and the right will
tribalize and get more aggressive and
you know i think a lot of people on the
right would be saying
10x more i think is if they didn't have
to
you know everything that they said would
be attached to trump
right they might oppose the guy
but you know if they voice any
opposition to any of this stuff it's
basically seen as support for trump
and they're not doing it as a result
so that's all going to that burden will
be lifted
and they'll be able to you know engage
online and do that kind of stuff so
it'll be cacophony it's going to be a
mess um if the
aid package isn't passed it won't be
passed and the economy will sink and
it'll crater next year and um
it's not going to get any better until
you know
we stimulate and vaccine our way out of
this thing
because a huge percentage of the economy
is you know still locked up and people
are staying home and they're not doing
stuff
um and it's going to be a a very very
uh aggressive four years i mean
look um there will be a big
detrumification effort
okay they're gonna go after people in
the government they're gonna go after
people
you know in private life that
participated in the government
uh criminal prosecutions i mean you know
kind of the petty corruption you see in
the trump side
you know is the stuff that everyone
seems to be focused on to go after
but versus like the huge corruption that
went on in the financial crisis that
everyone kind of they cost us
tens of trillions of dollars of damage
and everyone kind of papered over and
hid
um yeah that's going to be used as the
basis to
kind of go and with paris as a kind of
vp show honcho those
kind of you know detrompification
trials in congress and and honcho the
legal effort and hound everybody
who was tied to the trump administration
isn't that why they picked her oh yeah
no she's going to be she's going to be
the enforcer
they picked her to be the aggressive
prosecutor of the detrompification
effort
oh yeah and um and she will be good
she'll be fantastic at that role she's a
nightmare yeah and that that's going to
bleed over into private life and it
would give the kind of
you know thumbs up signal to all the big
platforms to do the same thing
and they'll you know to kind of take out
anyone
you know you saw the switch in the last
three four months as the cobit thing
started going is that
all of the uh kind of establishment
left started calling everything on the
right
fascist it just was a flip you know the
switch
the switch just flipped and otherwise
kind of you know people who are still
playing
about you know standard american rules
which is like discussion within a kind
of a center
uh arena you can call other people bad
names but not as a group right
uh is that all of the people on the
right
even in a moderate rate they're all
fascist and so it's
that means that every group everything
that that was
proposed on the right or operate on the
right is is considered a threat
now that the worry here is that any
given moment um
some knucklehead is going to go out
there and kill some people or do
something stupid like
kidnappa or kill a sitting governor
and somebody on the right who will then
make real
the fears that right-wing militias are
out there about to take over the
government kind of thing
and that they're a terrorist threat on
par with al qaeda
and that detrompification effort in the
government and you know just mostly a
legal side and and
corporate becomes a counter-terrorism
kind of counter-insurgency effort
that gets billions of dollars of funding
and you know tens of billions of dollars
funded in to try to then
root out this potential evil uh this
white supremacy
in action and that means like new powers
to kind of monitor
communications identify who's like
sympathetic
who's potential white supremacist who's
who's potentially contributing to these
groups
uh contributing with you know stochastic
terrorism you know
the idea that if you say anything that
could be construed as
say white supremacist if white
supremacist acts it's your fault
and the same thing we saw with islam
right so fundamentalist islam becomes
the problem um now how does that roll
out is that once you get that financial
feedback loop it just starts to sprawl
it starts to get huge uh and it goes
into all these efforts
no knock raids and weapon seizures and
uh monitoring of lots of people and
no fly lists and no job lists and things
like that
based on the sprawling
pattern recognition done by ai's and
done by
you know nobodies in the in the network
who are trying to say that this kind of
behavior is an example of
of uh extreme behavior now it's you know
it's
i think that i think people have already
switched over i just watching these
people
all of a sudden say all of these people
are fascists
based on some kind of weird notion of
what is fascist and therefore
you know enemies of all of us wow it was
just amazing to see that switch happen
it's just i don't see a commensurate
switch occurring on the right i you know
where everybody is
they have weird little funky names but
not like this evil incarnate name
um john you just kicked me in the gut
fir first of all i wanted an election
prognosis you didn't get pregnant
you did not give me that but i'm gonna
i'm gonna ask you again later
but um oh my god okay so i've been
saying
for a long time now that uh
if if the democrats win in 2020 there
will be a big effort to quote
not let that happen again and by that i
mean
trump right we can't let that happen
again it was just a
it's just an aberration it was just a
blip but we have to squash it we have to
extinguish it and we have to make sure
this
never happens again this fascism never
happens again and this will be the end
of the white supremacy
dominating culture and end of the
patriarchy and end of the systems of
white oppression and all that they're
going to use this as a chip
they're going to put their knee on my
neck john and they're going to try
to end us and i've been terrified of
that
and and for the life of me i could never
understand
why they picked freaking kamala harris
she's imminently unlikable actually
verifiably hateable she is
an anti-civil libertarian she doesn't
believe in people's rights she
prosecuted minor offenses she kept
people in jail when she shouldn't have
she didn't even win one stinking
delegate
but oh my god is she a prolific
prosecutor
and man now that you've put that in
context
uh for me i yeah she's not really my
stomach
yeah she's not really a political threat
dividing in popularity right and
she's also part of the kind of like i
mean her background is that she's
connected to the elites of the silicon
valley california elites she was very
early on
you know dated inside that group grew up
and you know
came to power inside that group um she's
extremely well connected
and um but she's not really likable on a
national stage
so she's not like a political
threat to biden and inviting there's
gonna be an uh nobody throughout the
thing he's just gonna
kind of be a fumbler and bumbler
and then the other thing that you said
here is corporations
acting as a counter-insurgent force holy
crap
that's also terrifying they see us as
insurgents we've even labeled ourselves
as insurgents the red insurgency
it is an insurgency against the new
party against the establishment
against the 50 years of unified rule
people that
about provide bouts of the corporations
and globalists
and immigration and all kinds of crazy
things we're definitely in surging
if that's a verb against that and you're
right it will be the corporations that
act as the counter-insurgency force
and that is actually really terrifying
when you think it all the way through
it does also prevent the detoxification
effort does present a ripe opportunity
for false flags or
encouraging people to do stupid stuff if
you're in a chat group and some guy's
like hey why don't we go bomb a federal
building
you know that guy is the narc don't
listen to him please
i fear that people will be egged on into
doing something really stupid
in order uh for the democrat elect
administration to
really clamp down on the
detrompification effort holy crap that's
a terrifying concept
yeah it's all it can do is just
accelerate the uh crackdown and the
crackdown could be total and could be
long-lasting so yeah only duper hard
please vote people please vote this
john's not making me feel very
optimistic about things john as it
stands today you think who wins the
election
and in what form do they win the
do they win popular do they would then
do an end electoral
do they win through the courts is this a
long disputed process
landslide one way or the other what do
you think
ah well i think as it stands right now
it looks like a
you know by going away and um
you know i was early on saying that
trump probably would win you know
2016. so unless there's some kind of
outlier some
surprise to some kind of twist um
i don't see the dynamic going in his
direction now granted he was this
low at the time of the access hollywood
tapes and other things in 2016 and he
could end up recovering like that but i
just don't
the lack of engagement on the biden side
and the kind of covet winner
kind of thing is just grinding and this
daily and it keeps on knocking out
participants and
knocking out chances for you know
disruption to
occur i just don't see the kind of
maneuver
strategy working in this in this
environment
um cove had changed i mean it turned in
what would look like a you know 80 90
chance that trump would walk in
to uh something decidedly different
and um yeah so i i don't think he's
gonna
win i you know hey you know
yeah it's just a you know it's this is
just a blip it's not like the
be all and end all right so it's it's
just you know a longer
tribal conflict and things like this it
could could last a decade
could be over really quick uh one side
you know really gets his act together um
gets the momentum going um but i don't
think the election really matters as
much as
most people but there is a tipping point
in terms of technology that's coming at
some point and
members in charge and whoever leads that
and and has power and control at the
time of the tipping point whoever does
the tipping
that is sort of a winner-take-all
situation so there is some sense of
urgency here with the presidential
election
ladies and gentlemen please run out
there and vote as they say in chicago
wrote early vote often just kidding but
really get out there and do something
because
yes it is just one battle in the larger
war
but the stakes are so high uh that it
is essential i think for people to
mobilize and
john you paint a very um depressing sort
of picture when it comes to the
determinification the corporation's
acting as a
as a counterinsurgency force and the
prospect of a long night
and so because of that we will continue
to do our work here we will continue to
do our work in the liminal order
uh that is where we're working to fight
against all these forces and provide
a walled off environment which you can
professionally network personally
network socialize communicate make sense
of the world get information
fine-tune your discernment learn how to
embody your ideals and have the
integrity the physical integrity to
carry that out
so if you're interested in that
masculinity sovereignty and brotherhood
come check us out liminal hyphen order
dot com
check me out on twitter
jackmurphylive.com and on the website
jackmurphylab.com get the book
democrats to deplorable on amazon go to
john rob's patreon sign
up the best patreon in existence no
question hands down the best value
you're gonna find out there
if you ever feel like i know what i'm
talking about it's only because i'm
listening to guys like john rob and
reading everything that he has to say so
john thank you so much for coming on
here is there anything you'd like to
leave us with
or um no i mean life goes on
right yeah so focus on your family focus
on you know living life
and uh do good and you know
this other stuff it's happening and
you'll have a
you play a part in it but don't let that
dictate your
life right don't let it wreck your life
just focus on
the here and now and the people around
you indeed especially the people around
you
your friends your family your community
your neighborhood your local connections
those will become more important than
ever so really focus on that i really
appreciate it john it's always an
extreme pleasure and honor to speak with
you
thank you so much i can't wait to do
this again probably sometime
around the inauguration or even after
the election if you're up for it
so thank you very much thanks everybody
for listening i really appreciate it and
uh we'll catch you guys soon
on the jack murphy live podcast thanks a
lot bye-bye